<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>ATÉRIOR Races</name>
    <description>ATÉRIOR custom races.</description>
    <author>Falling-Cats</author>
    <update version="1.0.0">
      <file
        name="Races/seryn-human.xml"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Falling-Cats/aterior-aurora/main/Races/seryn-human.xml"/>
    </update>
  </info>

  <element
      name="Seryn Human"
      type="Race"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACE_SERYN_HUMAN">
    <description>
      <h4>SERYN HUMAN</h4>

      <h5>Before the Weaver's Touch</h5>
      <p>
        Among humanity, some individuals have always demonstrated an unusual acceleration
        of potential. They learned faster. Adapted mid-crisis. Pushed past limits others
        hadn't yet found. Such individuals were never considered a separate people — the
        term Seryn arose informally, used to describe those who seemed to surge ahead when
        the moment demanded it. Most who carried the label never knew it had a name.
      </p>
      <p>
        They were not inherently stronger or wiser than others. They simply ignited faster.
      </p>
      <p>
        In times of peace, this set them apart quietly — the fast learner in the back of
        the room, the apprentice who outpaced their master without meaning to. In times of
        crisis, it made them invaluable. They were the ones others turned to before fully
        understanding why.
      </p>
      <p>
        Society did not formally distinguish them. A Seryn was simply described as gifted,
        driven, or built different. No ceremony marked them. No institution tracked them.
        They were recognized the way talent always is — by the people standing closest,
        watching them move.
      </p>

      <h5>After the Weaver's Touch</h5>
      <p>
        In a fractured world, Seryn humans became catalysts.
      </p>
      <p>
        When structures collapsed, they improvised. When plans failed, they adapted. When
        others hesitated, they had already begun. They are often the first to rise in
        uncertain conditions — not because they are chosen, but because they move before
        others can.
      </p>
      <p>
        Some became heroes. Some became tyrants. Most simply became the ones who moved
        first.
      </p>
      <p>
        But rapid growth comes with its own cost. Their instincts often outpace their
        experience. Their early success can place them in roles they are not fully
        prepared to hold. Among humans, talent draws attention — but effort still earns
        trust. A Seryn who relies only on natural ability is rarely respected for long.
      </p>
      <p>
        The most admired are not those who rise quickly. They are those who learn how to
        carry that rise without collapsing under it.
      </p>
      <p>
        Seryn are admired, relied upon, and sometimes quietly feared. Not for what they
        are — but for how fast they can become something more.
      </p>

      <h5>Appearance</h5>
      <p>
        Seryn humans are visually indistinguishable from other humans. There is no
        consistent physical marker that defines them.
      </p>
      <p>
        What sets them apart is presence.
      </p>
      <p>
        They often move with a subtle sharpness, reacting quickly even when at rest. Their
        focus can feel immediate and intense, as though they are always slightly ahead of
        the moment. In conversation, they may grasp meaning before it is fully spoken. In
        action, they adjust without hesitation.
      </p>
      <p>
        They do not look different. But they rarely feel ordinary.
      </p>

      <h5>Seryn Traits</h5>
      <p>
        Your Seryn Human character has the following racial traits.
      </p>
      <p>
        <span class="feature">Creature Type.</span>
        Humanoid.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>
        Increase one ability score by 2 and a different ability score by 1,
        or increase three different ability scores by 1.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Age.</span>
        Seryn humans mature and age at the same rate as other humans.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Size.</span>
        Medium.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Speed.</span>
        Your base walking speed is 30 feet.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Skills.</span>
        You gain proficiency in one skill of your choice.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Feat.</span>
        You gain one feat of your choice.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Languages.</span>
        You can speak, read, and write Common and one extra language of your choice.
      </p>

      <h5>On Being Seryn</h5>
      <p>
        Most Seryn do not think of themselves as Seryn.
      </p>
      <p>
        The label is external — applied by teachers, commanders, rivals, and the
        occasional scholar who noticed a pattern. Most simply think of themselves as
        people who work hard and move fast.
      </p>
      <p>
        The ones who do eventually learn the word often describe the same quiet
        realization: "I thought everyone felt this way."
      </p>
      <p>
        They do not. That gap — between what a Seryn assumes is normal and what actually
        is — is often where both their greatest strengths and their most costly mistakes
        are made.
      </p>

      <h5>Seryn in the World</h5>
      <p>
        Seryn are not a community. They have no gathering places, no shared traditions,
        no cultural identity built around what they are.
      </p>
      <p>
        They are simply people who burn a little faster than everyone else — and live with
        whatever that means.
      </p>
      <p>
        In practice, this shapes them in ways they often do not fully recognize. They tend
        to find themselves at the front of things — not because they sought leadership, but
        because they were already moving when others were still deciding. They attract
        attention without trying. They accumulate responsibility without always asking for
        it.
      </p>
      <p>
        Some carry this well. Others spend years learning that being first is not the same
        as being ready.
      </p>
      <p>
        Among adventuring parties, a Seryn often becomes the axis around which momentum
        builds — not always the planner, not always the strongest, but the one whose
        energy sets the pace. When a Seryn commits to something, the people around them
        tend to follow before they have fully decided why.
      </p>
      <p>
        That pull is not magic. It is simply what it looks like when someone moves without
        hesitation in a world that hesitates constantly.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet display="false"/>
    <rules>
      <stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>
      <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON"/>
      <select type="Language" name="Language (Seryn)" supports="Standard||Exotic"/>
      <select type="Proficiency" name="Skill Proficiency (Seryn)" supports="Skill"/>
      <select type="Feat" name="Feat (Seryn)"/>
      <select type="Racial Trait" name="Ability Score Method" supports="ATERIOR_ASI_METHOD"/>
    </rules>
  </element>

</elements>
