<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>ATÉRIOR Races</name>
    <description>ATÉRIOR custom races.</description>
    <author>Falling-Cats</author>
    <update version="1.0.0">
      <file
        name="Races/vaelorin-elf.xml"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Falling-Cats/aterior-aurora/main/Races/vaelorin-elf.xml"/>
    </update>
  </info>

  <element
      name="Vaelorin Elf"
      type="Race"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACE_VAELORIN_ELF">
    <description>
      <h4>VAELORIN ELF</h4>

      <h5>Before the Weaver's Touch</h5>
      <p>
        Before the Severing, the Vaelorin were skybound urban elves who dwelled within the
        great central kingdom at the height of its arcane-technological brilliance. While
        other peoples filled the streets and towers, the Vaelorin claimed the rooftops.
      </p>
      <p>
        They designed and maintained elevated gardens, vertical orchards, wind-harvesting
        terraces, and living skybridges woven with vine and spellcraft. They moved fluidly
        across the city's upper levels, treating rooftops and suspended walkways as others
        treated forest canopies. To them, architecture was terrain.
      </p>
      <p>
        Their magic focused on cultivated growth—controlled ecosystems sustained through
        careful arcane and botanical mastery. They were planners, terrace farmers, skyline
        pathfinders, and quiet guardians of breathable spaces.
      </p>
      <p>
        Though fully integrated into urban society, they favored open air and elevation
        over enclosed chambers. Even before the Severing, they were defined by movement. In
        crowded streets, they seemed distant. Above it all, they were exactly where they
        belonged.
      </p>

      <h5>After the Weaver's Touch</h5>
      <p>
        When the Weaver severed divine connection and destabilized arcane systems, urban
        infrastructure faltered. Irrigation enchantments failed. Skybridges collapsed.
        Vertical gardens withered without the magic that sustained them.
      </p>
      <p>
        The Vaelorin adapted.
      </p>
      <p>
        Survivors scattered beyond the ruined kingdom, carrying knowledge of cultivation,
        navigation, and environmental harmony. In the centuries since, they have become
        wilderness pathfinders, migratory orchard-keepers, monster hunters, survivalists,
        animal tamers, and horizon-watchers.
      </p>
      <p>
        Modern Vaelorin distrust confinement and fragile systems. They favor open skies,
        plains, highlands, coasts, and forest edges—places where visibility and mobility
        ensure survival. Their settlements are often temporary or seasonal, leaving minimal
        scars upon the land.
      </p>
      <p>
        Their philosophy centers on resilience through motion. They plant knowing they may
        not remain. They travel knowing the path matters more than the destination. They do
        not linger long enough for the world to depend on them. And they are careful never
        to depend on it in return.
      </p>

      <h5>Appearance</h5>
      <p>
        Vaelorin are lean and long-limbed, built for endurance and balance rather than
        ornament. Their movements are deliberate and economical, conserving energy even in
        stillness.
      </p>
      <p>
        Their ears are noticeably longer than those of most elven lineages, tapering into
        pronounced, blade-like points that sweep subtly backward. Among the Vaelorin, ear
        length is often regarded as a mark of lineage and perceptiveness.
      </p>
      <p>
        Most striking are their eyes. Nearly all Vaelorin possess the gaze of a
        predator—vertical slit pupils set within irises that often carry a faint inner
        luminosity. Eye colors commonly include deep emerald, amber, gold, storm-gray, or
        muted violet. In rare cases, individuals display unusual patterns such as fractured
        color bands, radial striations, or dual-toned gradients.
      </p>
      <p>
        To meet the eyes of a Vaelorin is to feel measured. They do not look at the world
        casually. They assess it.
      </p>

      <h5>Vaelorin Traits</h5>
      <p>
        Your Vaelorin character has the following racial traits.
      </p>
      <p>
        <span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>
        Increase one ability score by 2 and a different ability score by 1,
        or increase three different ability scores by 1.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Age.</span>
        Vaelorin mature at a rate similar to humans, reaching physical adulthood in their
        early twenties. However, they are not considered full members of their people
        until completing a formative period of travel and self-sufficiency, typically
        between the ages of 40 and 50. Vaelorin commonly live between 400 and 500 years,
        though few in the modern age reach the heights of longevity recorded before the
        Weaver's Touch.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Size.</span>
        Vaelorin have the slender build typical of elves. Your size is Medium.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Speed.</span>
        Your base walking speed is 30 feet.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Darkvision.</span>
        You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in
        darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Keen Senses.</span>
        You have proficiency in the Perception skill.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Fey Ancestry.</span>
        You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put
        you to sleep.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Trance.</span>
        You meditate deeply for 4 hours instead of sleeping, gaining the same benefit as
        8 hours of rest, remaining semiconscious.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Elf Weapon Training.</span>
        You have proficiency with the longsword, shortsword, shortbow, and longbow.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Cultivator's Cantrip.</span>
        You know one cantrip of your choice from the druid spell list. Wisdom is your
        spellcasting ability for it.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Extra Language.</span>
        You can speak, read, and write one extra language of your choice.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Wanderer.</span>
        You have excellent memory for maps and geography, recalling terrain and
        settlements. You can also find food and fresh water for yourself and up to five
        others each day, provided resources are available.
        <br/>
        <span class="feature">Predator's Eye.</span>
        Your eyes are trained to catch the smallest details—once to navigate impossible
        paths, now to survive a fractured world. As a bonus action, you focus your senses
        on a creature you can see within 60 feet. You instantly assess its condition and
        defenses. You learn whether the creature is above or below half its maximum hit
        points, as well as its Armor Class. You then gain advantage on your next attack
        roll against that creature before the end of your next turn. Once you use this
        trait, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet display="false"/>
    <rules>
      <stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>
      <stat name="darkvision" value="60"/>
      <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON"/>
      <select type="Language" name="Language (Vaelorin)" supports="Standard||Exotic"/>
      <select type="Racial Trait" name="Ability Score Method" supports="ATERIOR_ASI_METHOD"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_PERCEPTION"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_LONGSWORD"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SHORTSWORD"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SHORTBOW"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_LONGBOW"/>
      <select type="Spell" name="Cultivator's Cantrip (Vaelorin)" supports="Druid&amp;&amp;0"/>
    <element
      name="Darkvision"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_DARKVISION">
    <description>
      <p>
        You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in
        darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>You can see in dim light within 60 feet as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules>
      <stat name="darkvision" value="60"/>
    </rules>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Keen Senses"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_KEEN_SENSES">
    <description>
      <p>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_PERCEPTION"/>
    </rules>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Fey Ancestry"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_FEY_ANCESTRY">
    <description>
      <p>You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put you to sleep.</p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>Advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put you to sleep.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules/>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Trance"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_TRANCE">
    <description>
      <p>
        You meditate deeply for 4 hours instead of sleeping, gaining the same benefit as
        8 hours of rest, remaining semiconscious.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>You meditate for 4 hours instead of sleeping, gaining the same benefit as 8 hours of rest.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules/>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Elf Weapon Training"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_WEAPON_TRAINING">
    <description>
      <p>You have proficiency with the longsword, shortsword, shortbow, and longbow.</p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>You have proficiency with the longsword, shortsword, shortbow, and longbow.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_LONGSWORD"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SHORTSWORD"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SHORTBOW"/>
      <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_LONGBOW"/>
    </rules>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Cultivator's Cantrip"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_CANTRIP">
    <description>
      <p>
        You know one cantrip of your choice from the druid spell list. Wisdom is your
        spellcasting ability for it.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>You know one cantrip of your choice from the druid spell list. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for it.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules>
      <select type="Spell" name="Cultivator's Cantrip (Vaelorin)" supports="Druid&amp;&amp;0"/>
    </rules>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Extra Language"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_EXTRA_LANGUAGE">
    <description>
      <p>You can speak, read, and write one extra language of your choice.</p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>You can speak, read, and write one extra language of your choice.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules>
      <select type="Language" name="Language (Vaelorin)" supports="Standard||Exotic"/>
    </rules>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Wanderer"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_WANDERER">
    <description>
      <p>
        You have excellent memory for maps and geography, recalling terrain and
        settlements. You can also find food and fresh water for yourself and up to five
        others each day, provided resources are available.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>Excellent memory for maps and geography. Can find food and fresh water for yourself and up to five others each day, provided resources are available.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules/>
  </element>

  <element
      name="Predator's Eye"
      type="Racial Trait"
      source="ATÉRIOR"
      id="ID_ATERIOR_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAELORIN_PREDATORS_EYE">
    <description>
      <p>
        Your eyes are trained to catch the smallest details—once to navigate impossible
        paths, now to survive a fractured world.
      </p>
      <p>
        As a bonus action, you focus your senses on a creature you can see within 60 feet.
        You instantly assess its condition and defenses. You learn whether the creature is
        above or below half its maximum hit points, as well as its Armor Class. You then
        gain advantage on your next attack roll against that creature before the end of
        your next turn. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a
        long rest.
      </p>
    </description>
    <sheet>
      <description>Bonus action: learn a creature's HP threshold and AC within 60 feet, then gain advantage on your next attack roll against it. 1/long rest.</description>
    </sheet>
    <rules/>
  </element>

</elements>
